George Volodine Papers
George Volodine Papers
1910-1982
Volodine, George.
9 linear ft.
Correspondence, prints, and memorabilia (photographs, scrapbooks, theatre programs, etc.) pertaining to the Russian-American dancer and ballet master.
3181640
Biographical History
George Volodine (d. 1982) was a Russian-American ballet dancer, choreographer, and dance teacher.
Volodine began his career with a ballet troupe in Germany, then moved on to New York where he became the maître-de-ballet of the Metropolitan Opera Association. During his time as a dancer, Volodine created long lasting friendships with fellow dancers, including George Balanchine, Maria Tallchief, Tanaquil LeClercq, and others. After his time as maître-de-ballet he moved to Westport, Connecticut and opened the George Volodine School of Ballet. Here, he taught a multitude of ballet dancers including Marsha Ismailoff Mark and Patricia H. (Lee) Zeitlin.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Volodine Papers includes correspondence-subject files, engravings, George Volodine School of Ballet, photographs, printed material, scrapbooks, and writings by others.
Correspondence-subject files contain personal correspondence from Volodine's friends, such as George Balanchine and his wives Maria (Tallchief) and Tanaquil (Le Clerq), Leon Kelly, and Michael Mordkin. There is a miscellaneous folder of Russian letters, mainly handwritten, from unknown individuals.
Engravings consists of two booklets with engravings of various scenes for the Kaiserliches und Königliches Hoftheater zu Wien (Imperial and Royal Court Theatre of Vienna).
George Volodine School of Ballet contains material relating to Volodine's ballet school in Westport, Connecticut. Volodine kept many photographs and newspaper clippings about his school and students; the material in this series includes correspondence, photographs, printed material, and scrapbooks.
Photographs includes personal and professional photos of Volodine, candid and professional photos of fellow dancers and friends (many of which are signed), and a large number of candid photos of soldiers and civilians during the Spanish Civil War. Within Volodine's personal photographs are images from his birthday party in 1968, three photo albums, and two photos of Mourka the dancing cat portrayed as performing in ballet productions.
Printed material relates to colleagues such as George Balanchine, Mikhail Baryshnikov, Rudolf Nureyev, and Maria Tallchief, and dance companies such as Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, Ballet Folklorico, and New York City Ballet. Formats include magazine and newspaper clippings as well as souvenir programs for single performances and entire seasons. There are also issues of a number of dance-related publications such as Dance Index and Dance Magazine and some miscellaneous items.
Miscellaneous material consists of two scrapbooks and a few pieces of writing by others. One of the scrapbooks is of dancers and dance companies; the other contains newspaper clippings from the end of the first World War, gathered by an unidentified individual living in Los Angeles, California. The writings by others, all typescripts, include essays about Volodine by Leon Kelly and Jacques de Wolfe.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arranged alphabetically by topic, title, or type, then chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Dance and theatre; Volodine, George.; Balanchine, George.; Braggiotti, Francesca, 1902-1998.; Le Clercq, Tanaquil.; Kelly, Leon, 1901-1982.; Nureyev, Rudolf, 1938-1993.; Stravinsky, Igor, 1882-1971.; Tallchief, Maria.; Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1898-1957.; American Ballet Theatre.; Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo.; Ballet Theatre (New York, N.Y.); Bolshoi Ballet Company.; Mordkin Ballet Company.; New York City Ballet.; Opéra de Paris.; Royal Ballet.; Sadler's Wells Ballet.; School of American Ballet.; Ballet dancers -- Soviet Union.; Ballet dancers -- United States.; World War, 1914-1918.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; Engravings (prints); Photograph albums.; Souvenir programs.; Theater programs.; Concert programs.; Magazines (periodicals); Manuscripts for publication.; Dancers.; Dance teachers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advance notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1967 and 1982.
Inventory
- Correspondence-subject files
  - Balanchine, George, 1937-1938; 1954 (Box 1)
  - Balanchine, Maria (Tallchief), 1950 (Box 1)
  - Balanchine, Tanaquil (Le Clerq), 1967-1968 (Box 1)
  - Fairfield University, 1966-1967 (Box 1)
  - Hugo Gallery, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Kelly, Leon, 1950-1951; 1967 (Box 1)
  - Lodge, John Davis, Mrs. (Francesca Braggiotti), 1952-1955; 1961,; 1971-1973; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Mark, Marsha Ismailoff, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Mordkin, Michael Jr., 1947 (Box 1)
  - Petchkovsky, Michael, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Syracuse University, 1967; 1970-1971,; 1982 (Box 1)
  - de Wolfe, Jacques, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, English, 1945; 1948,; 1952-1956,; 1971,; 1978 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, Russian, 1910; 1940,; 1946-1947,; 1978 (Box 1)
- Engravings
  - Theater-Vorhang von Carl Rahl (Oversize 2)
  - Orpheus-fabel von Eduard Engerth (Oversize 2)
- George Volodine School of Ballet
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Building permit court case, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - Financial payments, 1947-1953; 1959 (Box 1)
    - Long Lots Junior High School, 1956; 1959 (Box 1)
    - The Waterburg Women's Club, Inc., 1958 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Celebrations (Box 1)
    - Photograph album (Oversize 3)
    - Students, 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Students (Oversize 1)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1942-1954; 1959,; 1963-1965,; 1971; 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Programs, 1944-1949; 1950-1953,; 1956,; 1959,; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Silver celebration party, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Scrapbook [unbound] (Oversize 4)
- Photographs
  - Artwork reproductions (Box 2)
  - George Volodine
    - Personal, 27 Apr 1968; birthday party (Box 2)
    - Personal, 1972; Buenos Aires, Argentina (Box 2)
    - Personal, 1916-1918; 1936,; 1947,; 1959,; 1962-1968,; 1973-1975; miscellaneous candid photos; 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Personal, miscellaneous candid photos (Oversize 1)
    - Personal, negatives (Box 2)
    - Personal photo album (Oversize 3)
    - Personal photo album (Oversize 5)
    - Personal photo album (Oversize 8)
    - Professional, 1917-1918; 1923,; 1937,; 1946 (Box 2)
    - Professional (Oversize 1)
  - Other dancers
    - Candids, 1952; 1962 (Box 2)
    - Professional, 1925-1926; 1929-1931,; 1934-1936,; 1943-1944,; 1950; 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Professional, 1937 (Oversize 1)
  - Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939; street scenes, soldiers, civilians; 6 folders (Box 3)
  - Spanish Civil War, 1939 (Oversize 1)
- Printed material
  - Individuals, clippings, mostly from newspapers
    - Balanchine, George, 1943-1944; 1954-1976; includes 2 folders of material rehoused from scrapbook and left in original order; 4 folders (Box 3)
    - Baryshnikov, Mikhail, 1974, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Le Clercq, Tanaquil, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Lodge, John Davis, Mrs. (Francesca Braggiotti), 1961-1964 (Box 4)
    - Nureyev, Rudolf, 1965; 1970,; 1974 (Box 4)
    - Stravinsky, Igor, 1929; 1954,; 1962,; 1971-1972 (Box 4)
    - Tallchief, Maria, 1951; 1954,; 1963-1965 (Box 4)
    - Tchelitchew, Pavel, 1945; 1952,; 1964,; 1967 (Box 4)
    - Volodine, George, 1934; 1947-1952,; 1962,; 1966,; 1973-1975 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, mostly (but not all) dancers (Box 4)
  - Companies, programs and clippings
    - American Ballet Theatre, 1941; 1962-1963; programs (Box 4)
    - Azuma Kabuki, 1954 or 1955; program (Box 4)
    - Ballet Caravan, undated; program (Box 4)
    - Ballet Folklorico, program (Box 4)
    - Ballet de Paris (Roland Petit), 1948; program (Box 4)
    - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1936-1947; programs; 7 folders (Box 4)
    - Ballet Russe de Monte Carlo, 1950-1951; 1954,; undated; programs; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - The Ballet Theatre, 1942-1945; 1950-1951; programs; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - The Bolshoi Ballet, 1959; 1962-1963,; 1966,; undated; programs; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Fokine Ballet, 1927; undated; programs (Box 5)
    - Georgian State Dance Company, 1960 or 1961; programs (Box 5)
    - Gran Ballet del Marques de Cuevas, 1956; programs (Box 5)
    - Leningrad-Kirov Ballet, 1965-1966; programs (Box 5)
    - Moiseyev Dance Company, 1958; 1961; programs (Box 5)
    - The Mordkin Ballet, 1937-1939; undated; programs (Box 5)
    - New York City Ballet, 1948; 1950-1951,; 1956,; 1965-1967,; 1975,; undated; programs; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - New York City Ballet, 1950; 1960-1961; clippings (Box 6)
    - New York City Ballet, 1965 (Oversize 1)
    - L'Opera de Paris, 1948; 1951-1952; programs; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - The Royal Ballet, 1949; 1953,; 1960,; 1967; programs; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - The Royal Ballet, 1965; 1975; clippings (Box 6)
    - Sadler's Wells, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
    - School of American Ballet, 1944-1947; 1954,; 1959; programs (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, programs, clippings (Box 6)
  - Magazines
    - Center, 1954; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Center, 1955-1956; 3 folders (Box 7)
    - Dance Index, 1946-1949; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Dance Magazine, 1945; 1950,; 1957,; 1960-1962.; 1964; 7 folders (Box 7)
    - Dance in the Spotlight, 1964 (Box 7)
    - Photography, Jun 1954 (Box 7)
    - Playbill, 1960-1961 (Box 8)
    - View, 1942-1943; 1946 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous clippings
    - Flooding in Fairfield County, Connecticut, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1935; 1948-1949,; 1955-1957,; 1960-1961,; 1964-1971,; 1975,; 1977,; undated; 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous programs
    - A-F, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts (Box 8)
    - M-V, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Westport Country Playhouse (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous (Oversize 1)
  - Miscellaneous items, book on Romanian folk art, issue of South African Archaeological Bulletin, small book of adages or proverbs, exhibit catalog of Venetian festival items at Ca'Rezzonico (1937), sales catalog from record company, etc.; 2 folders (Box 8)
- Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook, various ballet individuals and dance companies (Oversize 7)
  - "War Book", 1917-1918; scrapbook of clippings from Los Angeles newspapers, about the end of World War I (Oversize 6)
  - Writings by others (Box 8)